<appendix xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap" version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="./" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

	<title>Event Representation: <literal>java.util.Map</literal> Events</title>
	<indexterm><primary>map event representation</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>event</primary><secondary>Map representation</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
		This section provides information for using objects that implement the <literal>java.util.Map</literal> interface to represent events. 
    </para>

	<para>
		For NEsper .NET also see <xref linkend="appendix_dotnet_eventrep_map"/>.
	</para>
   
	<sect1 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_overview">
	   <title>Overview</title>
		<para>
			Events can also be represented by objects that implement the <literal>java.util.Map</literal> interface. 
			Event properties of <literal>Map</literal> events are the values in the map accessible through the <literal>get</literal> method exposed by the <literal>java.util.Map</literal> interface.
		</para>

		<para>
			Similar to the Object-array event type, the Map event type takes part in the comprehensive type system that can eliminate the need to use Java classes as event types, thereby making it easier to change types at runtime or generate type information from another source.
		</para>

		<para>
			A given Map event type can have one or more supertypes that must also be Map event types. All properties available on any of the Map supertypes are available on the type itself. In addition, anywhere within EPL that an event type name of a Map supertype is used, any of its Map subtypes and their subtypes match that expression.
		</para>

		<para>
			Your application can add properties to an existing Map event type during runtime using the configuration operation <literal>updateMapEventType</literal>. Properties may not be updated or deleted - properties can only be added, and nested properties can be added as well. The runtime configuration also allows removing Map event types and adding them back with new type information.
		</para>

		<para>
			After your application configures a Map event type by providing a type name, the type name can be used when defining further Map or Object-array event types by specifying the type name as a property type or an array property type.
		</para>

		<para>
			One-to-Many relationships in Map event types are represented via arrays. A property in a Map event type may be an array of primitive, an array of Java object, an array of Map or an an array of Object-array.
		</para>

		<para>
			The engine can process <literal>java.util.Map</literal> events via the <literal>sendEvent(Map map, String eventTypeName)</literal> method on the <literal>EPRuntime</literal> interface. Entries in the Map represent event properties. Keys must be of type <literal>java.util.String</literal> for the engine to be able to look up event property names specified by pattern or EPL statements. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The engine does not validate Map event property names or values. Your application should ensure that objects passed in as event properties match the <literal>create schema</literal> property names and types, or the configured event type information when using runtime or static configuration.
		</para>
	</sect1>
			
	<sect1 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_properties">
	   <title>Map Properties</title>
		<para>
			Map event properties can be of any type. Map event properties that are Java application objects or that are of type <literal>java.util.Map</literal> (or arrays thereof) or that are of type <literal>Object[]</literal> (object-array) (or arrays thereof) offer additional power:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Properties that are Java application objects can be queried via the nested, indexed, mapped and dynamic property syntax as outlined earlier. 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Properties that are of type <literal>Map</literal> allow Maps to be nested arbitrarily deep and thus can be used to represent complex domain information. The nested, indexed, mapped and dynamic property syntax can be used to query Maps within Maps and arrays of Maps within Maps. 					
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Properties that are of type <literal>Object[]</literal> (object-array) allow object-arrays to be nested arbitrarily deep. The nested, indexed, mapped and dynamic property syntax can be used to query nested Maps and object-arrays alike.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
			In order to use <literal>Map</literal> events, the event type name and property names and types must be made known to the engine via Configuration or <literal>create schema</literal> EPL syntax. Please see examples in <xref linkend="epl_createschema"/> and <xref linkend="config-java-util-map"/>.
		</para>
										
		<para>
			The code snippet below defines a Map event type, creates a Map event and sends the event into the engine. The sample defines the <literal>CarLocUpdateEvent</literal> event type via runtime configuration interface (<literal>create schema</literal> or static configuration could have been used instead).
		</para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[// Define CarLocUpdateEvent event type (example for runtime-configuration interface)
Map<String, Object> def = new HashMap<String, Object>;
def.put("carId", String.class);
def.put("direction", int.class);

epService.getEPAdministrator().getConfiguration().
  addEventType("CarLocUpdateEvent", def);]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			The <literal>CarLocUpdateEvent</literal> can now be used in a statement:
		</para>
		<programlisting>select carId from CarLocUpdateEvent(direction = 1)#time(1 min)</programlisting> 
		
		<programlisting><![CDATA[// Create a CarLocUpdateEvent event and send it into the engine for processing
Map<String, Object> event = new HashMap<String, Object>();
event.put("carId", carId);
event.put("direction", direction);

epRuntime.sendEvent(event, "CarLocUpdateEvent");]]></programlisting>
	
		<para>
			The engine can also query Java objects as values in a <literal>Map</literal> event via the nested property syntax. Thus <literal>Map</literal> events can be used to 
			aggregate multiple data structures into a single event and query the composite information in a convenient way. The example below demonstrates a <literal>Map</literal> event with a transaction and an account object.
		</para>
		<programlisting><![CDATA[Map event = new HashMap();
event.put("txn", txn);
event.put("account", account);
epRuntime.sendEvent(event, "TxnEvent");]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			An example statement could look as follows.
		</para>
		<programlisting>select account.id, account.rate * txn.amount 
from TxnEvent#time(60 sec) 
group by account.id</programlisting> 		
	</sect1>

	<sect1 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_supertype">
	   <title>Map Supertypes</title>
		   
	   <para>
		   Your <literal>Map</literal> event type may declare one or more supertypes when configuring the type at engine initialization time or at runtime through the administrative interface. 
	   </para>

	   <para>
		   Supertypes of a <literal>Map</literal> event type must also be Map event types. All property names and types of a supertype are also available on a subtype and override such same-name properties of the subtype. In addition, anywhere within EPL that an event type name of a Map supertype is used, any of its Map subtypes also matches that expression (similar to the concept of interface in Java).
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
		   This example assumes that the <literal>BaseUpdate</literal> event type has been declared and acts as a supertype to the <literal>AccountUpdate</literal> event type (both Map event types): 
	   </para>
	<programlisting><![CDATA[epService.getEPAdministrator().getConfiguration().
    addEventType("AccountUpdate", accountUpdateDef, 
    new String[] {"BaseUpdate"});]]></programlisting>

	   <para>
		   Your application EPL statements may select <literal>BaseUpdate</literal> events and receive both <literal>BaseUpdate</literal> and <literal>AccountUpdate</literal> events, as well as any other subtypes of <literal>BaseUpdate</literal> and their subtypes.
	   </para>
		<programlisting><![CDATA[// Receive BaseUpdate and any subtypes including subtypes of subtypes
select * from BaseUpdate]]></programlisting>

	   <para>
		   Your application Map event type may have multiple supertypes. The multiple inheritance hierarchy between Maps can be arbitrarily deep, however cyclic dependencies are not allowed. If using runtime configuration, supertypes must exist before a subtype to a supertype can be added.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
		   See <xref linkend="config-java-util-map"/> for more information on configuring Map event types.
	   </para>
   </sect1>

	<sect1 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_advanced">
	   <title>Advanced Map Property Types</title>

		<sect2 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_nested">
		   <title>Nested Properties</title>
			   
		   <para>
			   Strongly-typed nested <literal>Map</literal>-within-<literal>Map</literal> events can be used to build rich, type-safe event types on the fly. Use the <literal>addEventType</literal> method on <literal>Configuration</literal> or <literal>ConfigurationOperations</literal> for initialization-time and runtime-time type definition, or the <literal>create schema</literal> EPL syntax.
		   </para>

		   <para>
			   Noteworthy points are:
		   </para>

			<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>
						JavaBean (POJO) objects can appear as properties in <literal>Map</literal> event types. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						One may represent Map-within-Map and Map-Array within Map (same for object-array) using the name of a previously registered Map (or object-array) event type.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						There is no limit to the number of nesting levels.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Dynamic properties can be used to query <literal>Map</literal>-within-<literal>Map</literal> keys that may not be known in advance. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The engine returns a <literal>null</literal> value for properties for which the access path into the nested structure cannot be followed where map entries do not exist.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

		   <para>
			   For demonstration, in this example our top-level event type is an <literal>AccountUpdate</literal> event, which has an <literal>UpdatedFieldType</literal> structure as a property. Inside the <literal>UpdatedFieldType</literal> structure the example defines various fields, as well as a property by name 'history' that holds a JavaBean class <literal>UpdateHistory</literal> to represent the update history for the account. The code snippet to define the event type is thus:
		   </para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[Map<String, Object> updatedFieldDef = new HashMap<String, Object>();
updatedFieldDef.put("name", String.class);
updatedFieldDef.put("addressLine1", String.class);
updatedFieldDef.put("history", UpdateHistory.class);
epService.getEPAdministrator().getConfiguration().
    addEventType("UpdatedFieldType", updatedFieldDef);

Map<String, Object> accountUpdateDef = new HashMap<String, Object>();
accountUpdateDef.put("accountId", long.class);
accountUpdateDef.put("fields", "UpdatedFieldType");	
// the latter can also be:  accountUpdateDef.put("fields", updatedFieldDef);

epService.getEPAdministrator().getConfiguration().
    addEventType("AccountUpdate", accountUpdateDef);]]></programlisting>

		   <para>
			   The next code snippet populates a sample event and sends the event into the engine:
		   </para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[Map<String, Object> updatedField = new HashMap<String, Object>();
updatedField.put("name", "Joe Doe");
updatedField.put("addressLine1", "40 Popular Street");
updatedField.put("history", new UpdateHistory());

Map<String, Object> accountUpdate = new HashMap<String, Object>();
accountUpdate.put("accountId", 10009901);
accountUpdate.put("fields", updatedField);

epService.getEPRuntime().sendEvent(accountUpdate, "AccountUpdate");]]></programlisting>

		   <para>
			   Last, a sample query to interrogate <literal>AccountUpdate</literal> events is as follows:
		   </para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[select accountId, fields.name, fields.addressLine1, fields.history.lastUpdate
from AccountUpdate]]></programlisting>
	   </sect2>
		
		<sect2 xml:id="appendix_eventrepmap_array">
		   <title>One-to-Many Relationships</title>
			   
		   <para>
			   To model repeated properties within a Map, you may use arrays as properties in a Map. You may use an array of primitive types or an array of JavaBean objects or an array of a previously declared Map or object-array event type.
		   </para>

		   <para>
			   When using a previously declared Map event type as an array property, the literal <literal>[]</literal> must be appended after the event type name.
		   </para>

		   <para>
			   This following example defines a Map event type by name <literal>Sale</literal> to hold array properties of the various types. It assumes a <literal>SalesPerson</literal> Java class exists and a Map event type by name <literal>OrderItem</literal> was declared:
		   </para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[Map<String, Object> sale = new HashMap<String, Object>();
sale.put("userids", int[].class);
sale.put("salesPersons", SalesPerson[].class);
sale.put("items", "OrderItem[]");	 // The property type is the name itself appended by []

epService.getEPAdministrator().getConfiguration().
    addEventType("SaleEvent", sale);]]></programlisting>

		   <para>
			   The three properties that the above example declares are:
		   </para>
		   <itemizedlist>
			   <listitem>
				   <para>
					 An integer array of user ids.
				   </para>
			   </listitem>
			   <listitem>
				   <para>
					 An array of <literal>SalesPerson</literal> Java objects.
				   </para>
			   </listitem>
			   <listitem>
				   <para>
					 An array of Maps for order items.
				   </para>
			   </listitem>			   
		   </itemizedlist>
		   
		   <para>
			   The next EPL statement is a sample query asking for property values held by arrays:
		   </para>

		<programlisting><![CDATA[select userids[0], salesPersons[1].name, 
    items[1], items[1].price.amount from SaleEvent]]></programlisting>

	   </sect2>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
